<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" version="5.0" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 http://diglib.hab.de/rules/schema/ER/v0.4/europeana-regia.xsd" xml:lang="en">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Codicology Clozianus-fragment Ferdinandeum Cod. B I/61</title>
                <respStmt>  
                    <resp>Codicological description by </resp>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Patricia</forename>
                        <surname>Engel</surname>
                        <affiliation></affiliation>
                    </persName>
                </respStmt>                
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Zentrum für Informationsmodellierung – Austrian Centre for Digital Humanities, Universität Graz</publisher>
                <idno type="PID"><!-- hier wird beim Ingest der PID des GAMS-Objektes hineingeschrieben --></idno>
                <availability status="restricted">
                    <licence></licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <msDesc xml:lang="en" xml:id="innsbruck-BI-61">
                    <msIdentifier>
                        <country>Austria</country>
                        <settlement>Innsbruck</settlement>
                        <institution>Tiroler Landesmuseum Ferdinandeum</institution>
                        <repository>Bibliothek des Ferdinandeums</repository>
                        <collection></collection>
                        <idno>Cod. B I/61</idno>
                        <altIdentifier type="catalog"> 
                            <idno>Dip. 973-C</idno>
                        </altIdentifier>                       
                    </msIdentifier>
                    <head>
                        <title>Glagolita Clozianus</title>
                        <origDate notBefore="1001" notAfter="1100">11. Jh.</origDate>
                        <origPlace></origPlace>
                        <note>Glagolitic Old Church Slavonic canon miscellany</note>                      
                    </head> 
                    <msContents>
                        <textLang mainLang="chu"/> 
                    </msContents>
                    <physDesc>
                        <objectDesc form="leaf">
                            <supportDesc material="perg">
                                <support>
                                    <p>The <material>parchment</material> is most probably <material>goat</material>, the hair follicles are well visible; the hair sides are 1r and 2v, consequently the flesh sides are 1v and 2r. There are stains, which result from the colour of the goat. The upper edge of the bifolio seems to be stretched more than the rest, which hints toward the fact that this is the softer area of the skin, i.e. close to the belly. As the bifolio measures about 40 cm width from right to left, the goat might have been of app. 1 meter length as it might have been positioned like “A” (cf. sketch by Jiri Vnoucek where the page with the initial is on the left and the upper edge of the bifolio on the right).</p>
                                    <p>The big hole in the middle of the bifolio was there before writing started; this hints toward the fact that even second class parchment was good enough for the codex. This is also indicated by the size of the skin, which hints towards a grown animal; consequently, the parchment maker did not strive to produce best possible quality, but took a skin he could reach.</p>
                                </support>
                                <extent>
                                    <measure type="leavesCount" quantity="2" unit="folio">1 bifolium</measure>
                                    <dimensions type="leaf" unit="mm">
                                        <height></height>
                                        <width>400</width>
                                    </dimensions>
                                </extent>
                                <foliation></foliation>
                                <collation>
                                    <formula></formula>
                                    <catchwords></catchwords>
                                    <signatures></signatures>
                                </collation>
                                <condition>
                                    <p>In the centre of the fold we find remnants of the binding technique: i. e. slits 10 mm, 25mm, 160mm, 235mm and 250mm from the upper edge. However, there are also round sewing holes: 7 mm and 40 mm both pricked from outside. There are countless other piercings. They correspond with each other on both semifolios and were pierced from outside through to the second semifolio. The third use, so to speak, comes from the fact that the bifolio was folded twice to result in a 4 layer piece of somewhat more than 100 mm x 144mm, perhaps to stiffen something like a book cover?</p>
                                    <p>
                                        <list>
                                            <head>Deletions</head>
                                            <item>There is a scraping with a knife on the second line from the bottom on the 3rd page in the centre.</item>
                                            <item>There are also erased letters at the beginning of the 6th line from the bottom on the very same page.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                    <p>
                                        <list>
                                            <head>Damages</head>
                                            <item>The bifolio is <term ref="http://gams.uni-graz.at/thesaurus/gelatinization">gelatinized</term>.</item>
                                            <item>There are some tears.</item> 
                                            <item>There are also several cuts, one of which is on the second folio in the corner and astonishingly does not appear in the same position on the other half of the folio.</item> 
                                            <item>Another cut is in the upper area, which clearly appeared after the parchment had been made and not before, otherwise it would appear as a hole now as a result of the stretching procedure.</item> 
                                            <item>There is a black stain along the fold, possibly char coal? Strong cross wise folds.</item>
                                            <item>On the upper edge a strong fold, possibly from secondary use in a book binding.</item>
                                            <item>Broken parchment along the folds and elsewhere.</item>
                                            <item>There are numerous scratches.</item>
                                        </list>
                                    </p>
                                </condition>
                            </supportDesc>
                            <layoutDesc>
                                <layout ruledLines="40">                                     
                                    There are 40 lines on each folio, <dimensions type="lineHeight" unit="mm">
                                        <height>5</height>
                                    </dimensions> mm wide from each other, made with medium sharp tools from “inside”, i.e. solely from the flesh side. The lower two lines exceed the marginal lines towards the outer edge in an irregular way.
                                    They are terminated by 2 vertical lines on each page, 135 mm from each other. Prickings on the outer margins correspond with the line position. Interestingly, there is a groove along the pierced holes for the lines.
                                    They might represent rulings prior to pricking. That the prickings are on a “curved” line might derive from the distortion the parchment underwent over time.
                                </layout>
                            </layoutDesc>
                        </objectDesc>
                        <handDesc>
                            <handNote xml:id="handID" scribe="x" script="x" medium="inkType"><!-- @ optional; Ein handNote ideallerweise für jede Hand / Schreiber mit xml:id und locus für die genaue Stelle, foll. wo die Hand tätig war; alternativ ein handNote für kurze Zusammenfassung aller Hände.--></handNote>
                        </handDesc>
                        <scriptDesc>
                            <scriptNote script="x" medium="x">The ink is either tannin ink or an iron gall ink; however, to take a final decision on the sort of ink an instrumental analysis is preferable (see the spectroscopical analysis of 2011).</scriptNote>
                        </scriptDesc>
                    </physDesc>
                    <history>
                        <origin>
                            <origPlace/>
                            <origDate notBefore="0001" notAfter="0001"/>
                        </origin>
                        <provenance></provenance>
                        <acquisition/>
                    </history>
                    <additional>
                        <adminInfo>
                            <recordHist>
                                <source><!--Gives the source(s) for the current MS description (e.g. Summary description by X based on ... / Beschreibung adaptiert nach:) Source in bibl with date for the adaptation.-->
                                    <bibl></bibl> 
                                    (<date when="2021">2021</date>).
                                </source>                                
                            </recordHist>
                            <custodialHist>
                                <custEvent><!--List of custodial events such as photography and conservation--></custEvent>
                            </custodialHist>
                        </adminInfo>
                        <surrogates>
                            <p><!--List and description of the surrogates / verbal description of the available surrogates (e.g. multi- hyper spectral imaging of fols. X and Yetc.)--></p>
                            <ref/>
                        </surrogates> 
                        <listBibl>
                            <bibl/>
                        </listBibl>
                    </additional>
                </msDesc>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl> <!--die Editionsprinzipien und Verfahren, die bei der Kodierung des Textes angewandt wurden-->
                <p></p>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <listChange>
            <change></change>
        </listChange>
    </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <facsimile>
        <graphic url="" n="1r"/>
    </facsimile>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>
                <title>Transkription des Textes ... </title>
            </head>
            <p><pb n="1r"/> ... </p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>